<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Simon Bedford</title><link href="https://simonb83.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://simonb83.github.io/feeds/customer-experience.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://simonb83.github.io/</id><updated>2015-03-11T16:53:00-06:00</updated><entry><title>Do You Really Care About Your Customers?</title><link href="https://simonb83.github.io/do-you-really-care-about-your-customers.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-03-11T16:53:00-06:00</published><updated>2015-03-11T16:53:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Simon Bedford</name></author><id>tag:simonb83.github.io,2015-03-11:do-you-really-care-about-your-customers.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Many companies claim to be customer-centric , but in my experience most
of the time its just untrue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Claiming to be focused on your customers and their needs certainly
sounds like the right thing to say, and no-one would ever advertise that
they don’t care about customers, however in reality there is a world of
difference between companies that just say it, and those who live by it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how can you tell the difference? If you answer yes to the majority of
these questions, then the likelihood is that your company still has a
long way to go to be truly “customer-centric”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You find yourself working more on cost-cutting and re-engineering
projects than long-term investments in improving customer experience
and loyalty&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Top executives don’t spend time engaging with front-line
employees&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most people stop caring about customer metrics when conflicts arise
(i.e. with sales or other results)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Executives never speak to customers (applies equally to B2B or B2C)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Customer Experience is seen as being the responsibility of operations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Customer-facing non-sales roles pay below market&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People in the contact center spend a lot of time worrying about
Average Call Time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your top customer complaint is the same for 3 years in a row&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nobody knows what to do with or how to handle a complex customer
problem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your employee turnover is high, particularly in customer-facing teams&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may notice that 3 of these have nothing to do with customer
management, but instead are indicators of employee treatment and
engagement:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Executives don’t engage with front-line employees&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Customer service roles are poorly paid&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Turnover is high&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hands-down the best way to create outstanding customer loyalty is by
having dedicated and motivated employees, who enjoy what they do and who
are proud of where they work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this is the one area where I see companies fall down the most,
and I am always amazed when I work with people who say they aim to
provide the best service in the industry, but are unwilling to invest in
hiring the best people.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="customer-experience"></category></entry><entry><title>10 Ways to Improve your Startup Customer Service</title><link href="https://simonb83.github.io/10-ways-to-improve-your-startup-customer-service.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-02-27T16:51:00-06:00</published><updated>2015-02-27T16:51:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Simon Bedford</name></author><id>tag:simonb83.github.io,2015-02-27:10-ways-to-improve-your-startup-customer-service.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I came across an article recently about problems that customers have
been having with a popular and fast-growing tech startup. Mostly these
seem to be because of a lack of formalized customer service processes,
rather than any massive flaw in the underlying product, team or business
model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I figure that these sorts of growing pains must be pretty common for
companies in this position...where growth is so rapid that there almost
isn't enough time to catch up and put the right servicing structure in
place (at least this is my hypothesis for what is happening).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think one thing that people worry about is the costs of providing
solid, 24/7 service, but the truth is that good customer service and
experience don't have to cost the earth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact I think there is a lot that you can do on a tight budget to
really create a service culture that matches a beuatifully-designed and
useful product. To that end I came up with this list of ideas, which I
think any business could (and should) implement pretty quickly:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Set Expectations About Response Times&lt;/strong&gt; - People get pretty antsy
when they send a message or an email and then don't hear anything
back, particularly when they have a problem. They are probably
sitting there thinking &amp;quot;Oh my god. Why haven't they answered me? They
don't care about my problem. There must be something wrong&amp;quot;. So then
they send another message and another and it becomes a vicious cycle.
However, if you let them know how quickly they can expect a response,
say with an auto-reply, then at least they will be able to relax a
bit more and not wonder whether or not someone is ever going to
reply.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Try and Beat Those Expectations&lt;/strong&gt; - If you say you’re going to get
back to someone in 12 hours, then that is the minimum that is
expected. However its even better when you surprise them by beating
their expectations. For instance I love my web hosting company.
Whenever I get in touch I am told that someone will get back to me
within 1 working day, but I don’t think I have ever had to wait more
than a couple of hours for a response.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Voice is sometimes best&lt;/strong&gt; - One of the main concerns I have seen
raised is the lack of a phone number for critical problems. I know
digital service can be work very well, particularly for everyday
problems, but in general I subscribe to the philosophy of respecting
customer channel of choice, and when someone is stressing out about
something really big, then what they really want is to speak to
another human being. This doesn’t have to turn into a huge call
center and could, for example, be limited to outbound calls for
critical cases…but I think its really, really important to have the
option.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clear Escalation Process&lt;/strong&gt; - With so much going on, particularly in
an exciting and fast-growth environment, problems can get overlooked
or even lost among all the other day-to-day activities. Sometimes the
person who does pick up on the problem isn’t the right person to deal
with it, or they don’t have the authority to take action. Customer
Service should be a top priority for everyone from the front-line
employee up to the head of service. If someone identifies a customer
issue that isn’t getting resolved fast enough, then they need to know
exactly what they have to do to get the problem escalated until a
solution is found.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use Feedback Wisely&lt;/strong&gt; - One thing that differentiates customer
experience leaders is what they do with the feedback they receive,
both positive and negative. There are typically three levels of
response:
&lt;em&gt;i.Customer&lt;/em&gt; - fix the customer issue a.s.a.p (within 48 hours if not
sooner)
&lt;em&gt;ii. Process&lt;/em&gt; - understand what processes went wrong and how they
need to be fixed (within a month or so)
&lt;em&gt;iii. Strategy&lt;/em&gt; - think about how customer experience issues feed
into the overall company strategy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be more proactive than reactive&lt;/strong&gt; - one of the best things you can
do is to try and figure out what is hurting customers before they
have an opportunity to tell you. A great source of information is
front-line employees.There is a huge difference between companies who
are going out of their way to be customer-centric, and those who wait
for the results of their most recent survey&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Engage with Detractors&lt;/strong&gt; - detractors doesn’t have to mean the
formal NPS definition, but pretty much anyone who is mad at you, and
even more so those who start tweeting or writing about it. Ask them
if they are willing to spend some time with you to help you figure
out what you need to do to improve. Invite them to a working lunch.
There is an awesome story about a Chick-fil-A manager who invited a
detractor to come to a tasting with the chef to help perfect the
recipe.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shout about how you’re improving&lt;/strong&gt; - most companies ask for
feedback from customers and then go off and work on it internally.
One really cool idea for customer engagement is telling all your
customers about how you are using their feedback to improve, maybe
through a blog, tweets etc. Virgin Media is a great example here,
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.virginmedia.com/nps/BillingEnquiries.html"&gt;creating a
website&lt;/a&gt; for
telling their customers about all the customer initiatives they are
working on thanks to their feedback.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be known for being a customer advocate&lt;/strong&gt; - I have an American
Express card and I love it. Why? Because I know that Amex has my
back, and I know it because I see it every day and every time I
interact with them. Last year I was hit up for about $4,000 USD of
fraud on my card, but resolving it was the most painless process
imaginable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Passionate Employees&lt;/strong&gt; - This goes without saying, however I have
worked with far too many supposedly ‘customer-centric’ companies to
know that this doesn’t always happen. I am amazed by the number of
people who expect first class customer results, but then hire the
first person who comes along, pay them terribly and treat them even
worse. Zappos knows exactly what they are doing in this regard and
they are definitely a role model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</summary><category term="customer-experience"></category><category term="10ideas"></category></entry></feed>