<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Simon Bedford</title><link href="https://simonb83.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://simonb83.github.io/feeds/ideas.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://simonb83.github.io/</id><updated>2015-03-11T02:54:00-06:00</updated><entry><title>10 Science Communication Ideas</title><link href="https://simonb83.github.io/10-science-communication-ideas.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-03-11T02:54:00-06:00</published><updated>2015-03-11T02:54:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Simon Bedford</name></author><id>tag:simonb83.github.io,2015-03-11:10-science-communication-ideas.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It feels like we are in a a crisis of science education and
understanding. From overreaction and scare stories about Ebola, to the
spread of measles due to vaccination myths, it has become far too easy
for the general public to become influenced by scare stories and
fear-mongering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, it seems like every other day that I see stories and posts
on Facebook with titles like “Why honey is the best antibiotic” or “The
secret cure for cancer they don’t want you to know about”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my mind, a lot of this comes down to the fact that as a society we,
no longer seem to value science or scientists. There is something very
wrong when ‘not being good at maths’ is considered a badge of honour,
and non-scientific and discredited ideas are given so much weight and
media-coverage, particularly when it comes to issues which affect
society more broadly such as public health policy and climate change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To that end, here is a list of ideas (some more realistic than others)
for trying to reverse this trend with better education, communication
and engagement. Many of these are aimed more at children because I think
that is where we need to focus in order to make a real difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A compelling basic science book for the general public which doesn’t
just educate but really engages people and gets them excited about
science. For me this would need to:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be written by a non-expert who has spoken to and interviewed
enough scientists until they understand the ideas well enough to
be able to explain them to someone else&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Include not just the ideas, but also personal stories about the
people behind the ideas; my personal choice for the author would
be Bill Bryson.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Games and apps that explore specific concepts and help people to
learn in a fun way. Some nice existing examples include
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://t.umblr.com/redirect?z=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.historyofvaccines.org%2Fcontent%2Fillsville-fight-disease&amp;amp;t=NDA0NjExM2UzMjljMDM3YzhjNzBhN2JlNjliYTIyMGE1NzgwNGJkMSxWWkNQOFNxSA%3D%3D&amp;amp;b=t%3A8OtdUEzgn7QWMCk7O9GO0g&amp;amp;m=1"&gt;Illsville&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://t.umblr.com/redirect?z=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.earthprimer.com%2F&amp;amp;t=OTMyYjRjYmQ2ZThlYmQ2NjAxNzg5MTFlM2NiNWUyODFhMTRlYjA2NyxWWkNQOFNxSA%3D%3D&amp;amp;b=t%3A8OtdUEzgn7QWMCk7O9GO0g&amp;amp;m=1"&gt;Earth
Primer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Immersive gaming – An immersive world that players need to explore
and learn about in order to advance. For instance you might start
with atoms and then once you have solved enough challenges, unlock
further levels to move onto molecules or atomic power. The more you
explore, the more you learn and the more you can unlock and advance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Virtual Lab – an online lab through which people can interact from
afar in scientific experiments. Participants would be able to suggest
and vote on experiments, and then review and interpret data in a
collaborative, and probably guided/moderated fashion. This is rather
like the idea of
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://t.umblr.com/redirect?z=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.quirky.com%2Finvent&amp;amp;t=M2M4MjdiZDUxOTc1NjAxODcxMzEzM2VkMmViOTc4MzE4ODE4MTQzYixWWkNQOFNxSA%3D%3D&amp;amp;b=t%3A8OtdUEzgn7QWMCk7O9GO0g&amp;amp;m=1"&gt;Quirky&lt;/a&gt;
but for general science.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Community science labs – staffed science labs which give
disadvantaged children and those without access to proper resources
the chance to use microscopes, telescopes and other instruments, as
well as interact with young, passionate scientists.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More films and TV programs about science and scientists. There has
been a positive trend recently with The Imitation Game and The Theory
of Everything, but there are still countless amazing and compelling
stories which could be told: Marie Curie, The Double Helix, Darwin,
Copernicus, Isaac Newton, Louis Pasteur etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cereal Box Science – collaborate with cereal manufacturers to put
educational materials on the back of cereal boxes and scientific
collectibles inside (could also apply to other types of food
manufacturers).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cooking, Home Brewing and Mixology classes that teach adults both
techniques as well as underlying science, ideally in the lab or
kitchen. For theory &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://t.umblr.com/redirect?z=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.edx.org%2Fcourse%2Fscience-cooking-haute-cuisine-soft-harvardx-spu27x&amp;amp;t=YjM3YjMzYzk1MzZmM2E3MTZlY2E0MDE2YjcxNTMwZjNjOTUwZGNiZSxWWkNQOFNxSA%3D%3D&amp;amp;b=t%3A8OtdUEzgn7QWMCk7O9GO0g&amp;amp;m=1"&gt;this
course&lt;/a&gt;
is awesome, but nothing beats hands on practice and interaction.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Engage the world’s leading advertising companies in science education
campaigns. If Ogilvy can create awesome campaigns and commercials for
consumer products, I’m sure they’d have some pretty cool ideas for
science too. Maybe they could even be persuaded to do some ‘pro-bono’
work which could help them contribute towards their Corporate Social
Responsibility goals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Rock star scientists” - As long as children grow up and see sports
players, actors, musicians and reality TV stars getting all of the
fame, money and attention, then those are the 'occupations’ that they
will see as most valued by society.Maybe we can fight back by with
“rock star” scientist positions for the most talented young
scientists, who would be put more in the spotlight to act as role
models for young people, rather like what has happened in the UK with
Brian Cox.I know this feels a bit like the dumbing down and even
degradation of science, but honestly desperate times call for
desperate measures, and right now I feel like we’re in pretty
desperate times.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</summary><category term="10ideas"></category><category term="science"></category></entry><entry><title>10 Ideas for a better Airline Customer Experience</title><link href="https://simonb83.github.io/10-ideas-for-a-better-airline-customer-experience.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-02-13T16:45:00-06:00</published><updated>2015-02-13T16:45:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Simon Bedford</name></author><id>tag:simonb83.github.io,2015-02-13:10-ideas-for-a-better-airline-customer-experience.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bag management technology&lt;/strong&gt; - bags tagged with RFID chips which are
scanned as bags are loaded onto and taken off the aircraft. It would
be awesome to receive a message as you board saying &amp;quot;Don't worry,
your bag is now on-board the plane&amp;quot;, and then another when you get
off letting you know when your bag is on its way to you to be
collected&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Other types of &lt;strong&gt;entertainment options&lt;/strong&gt; - sometimes I have been on a
flight and unexpectedly finished the book I'm reading (maybe due to
an unexpected delay). It would be great to have the option of
borrowing another book while on board, perhaps electronically.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More &lt;strong&gt;relevant in-flight shopping&lt;/strong&gt; - I have always found in-flight
shopping options to be totally uninteresting. Perhaps I could order
my duty free (or other items) on the plane and then have it waiting
for me when I get off at the other end. This way I wouldn't have to
worry about carrying it until I get to my destination.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Boarding process&lt;/strong&gt; - this is the big one to solve. Maybe dedicated
queuing lanes per boarding group would work, or maybe randomized
boarding with 4 seats at a time being displayed on a board calling up
the next 4 people and eliminating the queues. Probably the most
important challenge to solve in my opinion.
(&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.wired.com/2014/11/whats-boarding-airplanes-takes-forever/"&gt;http://www.wired.com/2014/11/whats-boarding-airplanes-takes-forever/&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Personalized offers / pricing&lt;/strong&gt; - I typically always fly at the
same times of year on the exact same route. However I can't ever
remember having received some type of personalized email telling me
about the best prices for flights around those times of year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pick meal at check-in time&lt;/strong&gt; - when I check in online, I would love
to see what the two food options will be, and maybe make my selection
at that time. Maybe I could also pay more at this time to get a more
premium selection? Or pay at check-in to get a better wine selection?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Immigration guides&lt;/strong&gt; - Immigration is always a pain. All you want
to do is get through as soon as possible. Once I book a flight it
would be great to receive an email with a guide to the destination
airport and immigration process: average wait times, what forms I
will need to have filled out, guide on how to fill them out, how long
the walk is to immigration etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Live updated immigration wait times&lt;/strong&gt; - provide live information on
immigration average wait times as the plane lands, just like a
weather report&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overhead locker space&lt;/strong&gt; - another part of the process that stresses
me out. It always feels so unfair when I see a family with 4 enormous
suitcase-sized bags as their 'carry-on' luggage. Another hard one to
fix. Maybe people who travel with smaller carry on luggage could get
some sort of discount or incentive. Or reduce handheld luggage
allowance but increase checked luggage allowance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In-flight mood lighting&lt;/strong&gt; - on over-night flights when it is near
landing time and lights are switched back on to full strength, I
already feel pretty bad on waking up due to jet-lag, and the bright
lights don't help. Some sort of more gentle wake-up maybe with blue
tinted LED lighting would be much more pleasant. I have heard that
Qatar airlines already does something like this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</summary><category term="10ideas"></category><category term="customer-experience"></category></entry><entry><title>10 Ideas for Creating New Connections</title><link href="https://simonb83.github.io/10-ideas-for-creating-new-connections.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-02-11T02:53:00-06:00</published><updated>2015-02-11T02:53:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Simon Bedford</name></author><id>tag:simonb83.github.io,2015-02-11:10-ideas-for-creating-new-connections.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Dinner from around the world” club – invite 5 people you know (who
don’t know each other) from different countries to dinner, each
person has to bring a dish from their home country.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Degrees of connectivity” – choose a country at random from a world
atlas; choose a city at random from that country. The aim is to get
connected to someone who lives in that city. Ask someone you know if
they could connect you with someone who might be able to help etc.
Capture and publish all new connections made.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build a website where people can post their networking requests (i.e.
who they would like to get in touch with and why), and other people
can come along and see if they can help out. You can earn
points/credibility by creating connections, or lose credibility by
only asking for help and not helping others.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Speed networking” – organize event at a bar, anyone can sign up, you
get 2-3 minutes to introduce yourself and then move on to the next
person.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Business card raffle” – find a location to collect business cards
(can even just be bit of paper with contact details) i.e. coffee
shop. When enough cards have been collected, pair people up randomly
who then have to meet over coffee. Make sure rules are clear for
people who leave their cards.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Virtual business card raffle” – for a group of interested people
i.e., a LinkedIn or other group, pair them up randomly and the pairs
have to contact each other and learn more about each other by email /
skype / phone etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Pay it forward coffee” – offer to pay for coffee for the first
person who responds to a post / blog / tweet etc. Meet up and get to
know them. They pay you back by doing the same thing etc. Capture all
new connections made on a simple website (could be quite cool
visually).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Pop-up networking” – in fairly central public area, create pop-up
event around lunchtime where anyone can drop by to meet other people.
Consider having a specific theme to help target to right individuals
i.e., tech, sports, bloggers etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a website / Linkedin / Facebook group for your area where
people can publish the biggest challenge they are currently trying to
solve (professional, personal project, life goal etc.). Others can
come along and contact if they think they can help.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build an app that lets people capture their route to work and/or
other routes they frequently take; publish anonymized route maps; let
other people place geo-tagged requests for knowledge, skills etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</summary><category term="10ideas"></category><category term="networks"></category></entry></feed>