<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Simon Bedford</title><link href="https://simonb83.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://simonb83.github.io/feeds/tech.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://simonb83.github.io/</id><updated>2016-02-01T17:49:00-06:00</updated><entry><title>Chef Jarvis - Your AI Sous-Chef</title><link href="https://simonb83.github.io/chef-jarvis-your-ai-sous-chef.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-02-01T17:49:00-06:00</published><updated>2016-02-01T17:49:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Simon Bedford</name></author><id>tag:simonb83.github.io,2016-02-01:chef-jarvis-your-ai-sous-chef.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;div class="section" id="the-concept"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. The Concept&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://simonb83.github.io/images/chef_jarvis.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AI Sous-Chef&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ever find yourself needing to manage several key steps at the same time?
Fear no more, your digital sous chef can help you multi-task like never
before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chef Jarvis automatically integrates with all of your smart appliances
giving you several extra pairs of hands in the kitchen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recipe Manager&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you find that you can’t remember if you used 600g or 900g of flour
for your cake last time or how long it took to bake in your oven? Do you
like to experiment with recipes, quantities and timing?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chef Jarvis lets you annotate, modify and store every aspect of your
recipes on-the-fly. Plus with in-built version control, you will have
full access to every version of the recipes behind your signature
dishes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tailored Suggestions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not sure what to cook tonight? Maybe you have a vague idea in mind but
are looking for some inspiration?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Chef Jarvis suggests dishes and finds recipes based upon key&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;ingredients, cuisines, cooking techniques, preparation time or even
wine or&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;beer pairings.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Over time, Chef Jarvis learns through its interactions with&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;you, making its recommendations more personalized to your preferences
and style&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;of cooking.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Workflow Control&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Overcooked meat, burned vegetables and frantic last-minute scrambles
are a thing of the past. Chef Jarvis keeps you on-track with all of
your recipes whether you are&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;cooking a single dish for supper or a multi-course haute cuisine meal
for your friends.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By carefully tracking your progress through all of your active recipes,
Chef Jarvis can warn you in advance of key upcoming steps and set alarms
for time critical activities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, Chef Jarvis automatically takes care of conversions between
imperial and metric systems, scales quantities, translates ingredients
or suggests alternatives so that you can concentrate on the cooking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Smart Shopping Lists&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you have selected your recipes, Chef Jarvis automatically adds the
necessary ingredients to your smart shopping list on the device of your
choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you often work with recipes from across the world?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chef Jarvis has you covered by automatically translating exotic
ingredients into locally-available alternatives as well as finding
nearby shops for buying the more unusual items.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conversational Interactions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Juggling multiple dishes and utensils with messy or wet fingers doesn’t
leave you much flexibility for interacting with a computer or other
device.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chef Jarvis listens for and responds to your commands and makes you feel
like you have a real assistant at all times in the kitchen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="background"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Background&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cooking has been a favourite hobby of mine for many years. However much
of the time I find myself working alone in the kitchen trying to
multi-task between various complex steps in concurrent recipes, all the
while re-washing and drying my hands to return to my computer or phone
in order to look up the next step, calculate quantities for ingredients,
convert between cups and grams etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Separately, I have also been trying to study the principles behind
machine learning techniques and in particular neural networks (fantastic
introduction by Michael
Nielsen&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://neuralnetworksanddeeplearning.com/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), and have
long been interested in trying to link my interests in cooking and
technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;One day I was reading about Artificial Intelligence&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;applications focused on home control systems, and I started wondering
about more specialized applications for very specific tasks. It dawned
on me that I could be far faster and more efficient working in the
kitchen if I could automate everything to do with following recipes
whilst trying to do something else with your hands, and so I started
to develop the idea from there.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The name is (obviously) inspired by Iron Man, as in my head I imagine
the helper to be as useful, friendly and easy-to-interact-with as Jarvis
is for Tony Stark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="some-thoughts-on-implementation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Some Thoughts on Implementation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are just some very high level thoughts on how I might go about
taking the first steps to implement something like this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recipe Parsing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A key requirement would be for the AI to be able to identify what a
recipe looks like as well as break it down into sections (i.e.
ingredients vs. method), as well as subsections (individual steps in
method etc.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the face of it, this doesn’t look too hard as recipes themselves
often have headings like Ingredients and Method, however I’m sure in
this case the devil is in the detail. For instance you could start to
think of ingredients as having some sort of predefined format {number -
unit - ingredient}, however often some sub-quantity of ingredients are
used multiple times in the method so you would need to be able to
distinguish between many different cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a start I would probably put together some type of web scraper to
grab a large number of recipes from sites like BBC Cooking, SeriousEats,
Chowhound etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I might use some kind of supervised learning to begin to break
recipes down into their individual elements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recipe Storage&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once a recipe has been parsed then it can be stored locally for the user
in some type of database structure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would look to integrate version control like git so that, for each
recipe, the user is able to create and store copies, modifying specific
elements. So for instance if the base recipe calls for 1kg of flour for
serving 10 people, and you want to save a version scaled down for
serving 4 people, then you would be able to store a modified copy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly if you find that you needed a higher oven temperature, longer
cooking time or any other type of change, then you can store your own
personalized version of that recipe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Basic Helper Methods&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I consider these to be some of the simpler requirements to implement,
that is for things like using voice commands to convert between
measurement systems, translate foreign ingredients or even suggest
alternative ingredients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently you could probably do much of this with Siri, however in this
case I think the problem is far narrower and better-defined (i.e., you
don’t need to be able to process all natural language, just very
specific commands for executing very specific functions).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So perhaps for conversions you could (at least at the start) use a
specific command phrase to indicate that the AI will need to listen out
for 1) a number, 2) input unit and 3) output unit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For being able to suggest alternative ingredients, you could start by
creating a large dictionary with common alternatives for harder-to-find
ingredients (many cooking sites already have these types of lists).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Integrating with Appliances&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I think that just the recipe-management functionality could be a
big help while cooking, it would also be fantastic for this type of AI
to help you with controlling kitchen appliances too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The very futuristic version would be just like Jarvis, with some sort of
robotic arm that could move around and actually interact with items in
the kitchen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously this is a far-fetched scenario, however more immediately I am
seeing a move by appliance manufacturers to building devices that you
can control via apps. For example I was recently given as a present a
small Anova Sous Vide machine, which can be controlled from an app
including turning it on and off, changing the temperature, setting a
timer etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Potentially as more appliances emerge with associated apps, then a
kitchen AI could use those interfaces to give you the ability to
interact with appliances using only voice commands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Command and Control&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A key part of the value of this sort of AI would be the ability to
interact with it hands-free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned before, this problem could probably be reduced (somewhat)
in complexity by defining specific commands that can be used to activate
certain functions. Another gift I received last Christmas was the BB8
robot by Sphero which has a small list of in-built voice activation
commands that work surprisingly well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So similarly you could program it to a list of 5-10 voice commands for
things like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conversions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set alarm&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get next step&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get ingredient amount etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</summary><category term="ai"></category><category term="cooking"></category><category term="deep-learning"></category><category term="machine-learning"></category></entry><entry><title>Crypto-currencies and the future of payments - Part I</title><link href="https://simonb83.github.io/crypto-currencies-and-the-future-of-payments-part-i.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-02-23T16:50:00-06:00</published><updated>2015-02-23T16:50:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Simon Bedford</name></author><id>tag:simonb83.github.io,2015-02-23:crypto-currencies-and-the-future-of-payments-part-i.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently I have been trying to understand the ideas behind Bitcoin and
other crypto-currencies and to think about what they might mean in the
long-term for more traditional payments companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Bitcoin protocol has some pretty neat ideas behind it and is
generating a lot of interest and excitement. Something that makes it
particularly cool is that, more than being purely transactional, it is a
politically-independent alternative currency with no central controlling
body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, payments is about so much more than just the transfer of money
(or other forms of value) between people, so there is a lot more work
that needs to be done before Bitcoin (or another crypto-currency) could
seriously start to challenge existing mechanisms like payment cards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a draft version of a white paper I have been working on,
analysing the payments value chain and how it might possibly be
disrupted by a crypto-currency:&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/98312054/Cryptocurrencies%2C%20Block%20chains%20%26%20the%20Future%20of%20Payments.pdf"&gt;Cryptocurrencies, Block chains &amp;amp; the
Future of
Payments?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think a fair summary of my current thinking is that there is too much
additional value provided by banks and card issuers, especially to
consumers, that is not currently offered by Bitcoin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In particular, until things like lending, consumer protection through
mechanisms like chargebacks, and maybe even rewards are integrated into
crypto-payment solutions, I really can't see them disrupting payments
for normal, every-day transactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are, potentially, some pretty interesting hybrid solutions which
incorporate the best of both worlds, and I discuss some of these
alternatives in the paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course it's more than likely that I'm wrong. My intention is to
discuss some of my ideas as well as other, alternative viewpoints, in
future posts.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="bitcoin"></category><category term="crypto-currencies"></category><category term="payments"></category></entry></feed>